A Guide to the The Paul Victorius Evolution Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Paul Victorius Evolution Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3314
This collection consists of 153 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Paul Victorius of Charlottesville, Va. by an anonymous donor to the University of Virginia Library.
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence by or about men who contributed to the development of the theory of evolution. Correspondents include Erasmus Darwin regarding the "Botanic Garden" and treating a patient with foxglove tea; James Hall to Alexander Marcet regarding introductions and recommendations, several societies, political ambitions and family news particularly the illness (delirium) of his son; and Wilhelm von Humboldt on Charles Darwin, Robert Fitzroy and the H.M.S. Beagle.
Also Herbert Spencer on his work and publications including "Principles of psychology," Darwin, Thomas Huxley and a bust of himself; J. F. W. Herschel on meteorology, geology and volcanic action; Charles Darwin on his health, work, father, human expression, the theory of language and Weale and Lyell.
Also Francis Galton on Darwin, differences with William Flower, and anthropomorphic experiments; and Samuel Butler on his theory of unconscious memory.
There are also water-colors of the H.M.S. Beagle by Conrad Martens; engravings of fossils; notes on the effect of alcohol and a prescription by Erasmus Darwin; and a ticket and a program for Charles Darwin's funeral, and a copy of his queries on human expression.
In addition there are pertinent news clippings and cartoons; and portraits of Darwin, his family, Robert Chambers, Hooker, James Hutton, Huxley, Lyell Spencer and John Tyndall.
Additional correspondents and recipients include Archibald Alison, Joseph Edgar Boehm, John Chapman, Emma Wedgwood Darwin, Francis Darwin, Robert Fitzroy, William Henry Flower, James Hall, Joseph Dalton Hooker, Thomas Henry Huxley, Joseph Johnson, Charles Lyell, Richard Owen, Thomas Percival, John Playfair, Anna Sedgwick, Alfred Russel Wallace, James Philip Mansal Weale and William Whewell.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
In addition to the manuscripts described below, the Paul Victorius Evolution Collection includes 814 printed books and pamphlets, all relating to the discoveries of Charles Darwin and his contemporaries including: Herbert Spencer, Sir Joseph Hooker, Thomas Huxley, Richard Owen, Charles Lyell, and Alfred Wallace.
Among the highlights of the collection are: Lyell's annotated copy of Darwin's Narrative of the Surveying Voyages of His Majesty's Ships Adventure and Beagle, Between the Years 1826 and 1836 (1839); the only known copy of Descent of Man inscribed by Darwin (1871); one of two copies of Herbert Spencer's Proper Sphere of Government, (1843) in the United States; a copy of the first edition of On the origin of the Species by Means of Natural Selection with manuscript notations (1859); an advance copy of The Power of Movement in Plants (1880) with corrections and annotations in Darwin's hand; a presentation copy of Insectivorous Plants (1875); and, the proof copy of Darwin's A Posthumous Essay on Instinct (1883).
Contents List
- John Playfair to Archibald Alison, 1878 [i.e. 1778] March 5 (Thursday), ALS, 1 p.; with attached partial address leaf. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Concerning an invitation.
- E[rasmus] Darwin to Mr. Johnson, Bookseller, 1784 May 23, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Derby, England, May 26. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Concerning the possible publication of Darwin's poems as "second part of the botanical garden." Asks that his name be not "affixed to this work on any account," as he thinks it would be injurious to him in his medical practice.
- E[rasmus] Darwin to Dr. Percival, M.D., 1787 September 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Concerning a paper; treating a patient with foxglove tea; Mr. Abraham Bennett's instrument for "doubling electricity"
- [James Hall] to M. de la Rive and [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1794 November 20, AL (in French), 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Regarding their leaving France; a letter of recommendation.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1795 January 3, Concerning Marcet's return to France, and Hall's plans to visit him. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Prescription written by E[rasmus] D[arwin]for Mrs. Ward, 1797 November 20, ADS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:6)
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1800 April 2, ALS, 1 p.; with address on verso; docket; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Re a party. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1800 July 16, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1800 July 21. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Re recommendation to Berthollet, Laplace, and Sequin for Marcet.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, [1800], ALS, 1 p.; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Impossible to meet Marcet that evening, and asks that mention be made "according to the foreign mode" of his membership in the Royal and Antiquarian Societies of Edinburgh when publishing his paper. With partial wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1801 March 22, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Introduction of Hall's brother-in-law, Lord Selkirk. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1803 May 20, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1803 May 25. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Re Marcet's friends Mr. Caramer; Mrs. Marcet's approaching confinement.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1806 May 29, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1806 May 29 (Box-folder 1:12)
  Regrets he could not dine with the chemical club; mentions his candidacy for representing Kirkendbright Co. at next general election; seeks Mr. Shaw's support in exchange for seat on India Company's board of directors. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1807 December 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1807 December 23. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Re Mr. Buccholz's experiments; inquires about [Humphrey?] Davy's illness.
- J[ames]Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, [1808] February 24, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1808 February 24. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Hall cannot visit because of an "invitation to dinner from the Seaker."
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1811 May 22, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Introduces Professor [Sir John] Leslie. Leslie was the inventor of "an apparatus for the production of cold,"with which he was the first to make artificial ice."
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1811 September 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached partial address leaf; docketed; postmarked September 3; in mylar sleeve with Japanese rice paper along brittle folds. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Requests help in London for his son William who has suffered an "attack of delirium." With wax seal.
- James Hall to [Dr. Alexander John Gaspard Marcet], 1811 September 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Re his son William's delirium; requests Marcet to find a person to follow him.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1811 October 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Re the illness of Hall's son, William. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1812 January 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1812 January 5. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Re Hall's son's illness, and his determination not to resign from geological society. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1812 January 20, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; docketed. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Giving his reasons for resigning from geological society.
- James Hall to [Dr. Alexander John Gaspard Marcet], 1812 June 27, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Re Hall's son's illness.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1813 June 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Dunbar 1813 June 10. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Re Hall's paper on the revolutions of the earth; sending two copies to Mr. Pictet in Paris. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1815 April 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1815 April 21. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Re forwarding a letter through Mr. Pictet to Hall's son in Geneva. With wax seal.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1815 June 2, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked 1815 June 5. (Box-folder 1:24)
  Re his son William's illness, and his son, John, in Geneva.
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, 1817 July 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Dunbar, 1817 July 18. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Re death of Hall's daughter Helen; election of their friend Basil to the Royal Society. With wax seal.
- James Hall to [Dr. Alexander John Gaspard Marcet], 1817 December 5, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Re Hall's son's illness, and his "plan of the university on the continent."
- Lady Helen Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet 1822 July 13, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Dunbar 1822 July 13. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Re William Hall's illness. With wax seal.
- W[ilhelm] v[on] Humboldt to Unidentified, 1839 October 3, AL, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Draft in German, re Travels in Arabia; mentions Charles Darwin accompanying Fitzroy on the H.M.S. Beagle expedition; with English translation. Item brittle and in disrepair.
- C[harles] Darwin to Smith & Elder, 1843 October 27, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked 1848 October 27. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Re payment by the treasury.
- A[dam] Sedgwick to "My dear Marshall," 1845 July 25, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Discussing Robert Chamber's Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation, and a possible visit.
- [William] Whewell to "My Dear James," 1846 January 5, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:31)
  Re furnishings for James' church; Whewell discusses a new edition of his Indications of the Creator as a response to the publication of Robert Chamber's Explanations: A Sequel to the Vestiges of the Natural History of Creation.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1851 May 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Re the Westminster Review; articles on communism; Spencer's work on the population question; Martineau; a "second edition of the education pamphlet;" [Horace?] Greeley and the Tribune.
- E[mma] D[arwin] [Mrs. Charles Darwin] to Mrs. Horner, 1851 May, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Re death of Darwin's daughter, Anne Elizabeth, and Mrs. Darwin's coming confinement.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1855 July 11, ALS, 5 pp. on 2 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Re retaining copyright for "The Philosophy of Style."
- Richard Own to [Mr. Marshall,] 1857 November 18, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Accepting an invitation.
- J[ohn] F[rederick] W[illiam] Herschel to J. G. Marshall, 1858 June 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:36)
  Concerning the study of meteorology, and defending the concept of atmospheric waves.
- J[ohn] F[rederick] W[illiam] Herschel to "My dear Sir" 1858 August 1, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:37)
  Concerning geology and volcanic action.
- Herbert Spencer to "Dear Sir," 1859 May 6, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:38)
  Concerning his health; strain and expense of new publications, and "a year and a half after the publication of the Principles of Psychology [he] was obliged to refrain from writing."
- H[erbert] S[pencer] to [John] Chapman, 185[9] November 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Proposes two articles on the development question, one "destructive and the other constructive." The first "a crushing criticism of arguments of opponents," and the other "the presentation of a coherent shape of the enormous amount of valid evidence" for the theory of development. His letter mentions Thomas Huxley and Charles Darwin, and provides a rough sketch of the contents of the two articles.
- Robert Fitzroy to "Dear Sir," 1859 December 1, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:40)
  A thank you note, mentioning himself and Darwin as opponents. Preservation tape along fold.
- J[ohn] F[rederick] W[illiam] Herschel to "My dear Sir," 1860 August 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:41)
  Concerning winds and the Gulf of Mexico. Hinged to sheet.
- Charles Darwin to "Dear Sir," [1865] May 16, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:42)
  Concerning a proposed "ice treatment" for "acid and morbid secretions" of the stomach.
- [Charles] Darwin's medical history, 1865 May 20, AN, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:43)
  Darwin's notes on his persistent stomach illness.
- Ch[arles] Darwin to "My Dear Sir," 1865 June 7, ALS, 5 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:44)
  Concerning Darwin's stomach illness, including his "three or four fits of flatulence every day," and the effects of ice treatment.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1866 December 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:45)
  Thanking Chapman for a copy of Cholera and Diarrhea, and mentions preparing for a second edition of the Principles of Psychology.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1867 February 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:46)
  Concerning an essay on the "Origin and Function of Music."
- Ch[arles]Darwin to [James Philip Mansel Weale?], [1867?] February 27, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:47)
  Concerning distributing Darwin's queries on human expression.
- Charles Darwin to F. [sic] P[hilip] Mansel Weale [1867], August 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope, postmarked. (Box-folder 1:48)
  Concerning plants native to the Cape of Good Hope; observations on human expression by a brother of a Kaffir chief. Thanks Weale for information about children pouting and claims that this expression is also found among Indian children. Disagrees with the French who claim there is "a grief muscle," and describes the muscles of the face involved in frowning. He also thanks him for a specimen of locust dung, and mentions experimenting on the dung for seeds.
- "Queries about Expression" compiled by Charles Darwin, [1867], ANsS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:49)
  A series of numbered queries about a variety of facial and bodily expressions, containing entries on astonishment, shame, excitement, sneering, contempt, head nodding, and others. Mentions that observations of "natives" who had had little contact with Europeans would "be most valuable." Darwin also claims that "general remarks on expression are of comparatively little value," and that "memory is so deceptive in subjects like these" that he hopes it may not be trusted to.
- Ch[arles] Darwin to J.P. Mansel Weale, [1868] January 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; postmarked London 1868 February 7. (Box-folder 1:50)
  Congratulates Weale on his marriage, and claims there is "great charm in a settler's life." Darwin also suggests that were Weale to remain in England, he could assume the botanical chair at Oxford. Mentions information on human expression, and laments the lack of "progress of civilization in South Africa." Mentions a photograph of a Bushwoman from Huxley. Discourages Weale's continued work on glacial activity in the southern hemisphere.
- Francis Galton to "My dear Farrar," 1869 December 14, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box-folder 1:51)
  Thanking Farrar for reviewing Galton's book.
- Francis Galton to "My dear Farrar," 1869 December 24, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:52)
  Mentions Charles Darwin, and reviews of Galton's book on hereditary genius. Hinged to sheet.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1870 February 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:53)
  Concerning Chapman's article.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1870 February 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:54)
  Declining an invitation to attend a committee meeting and "take part in the agitation."
- Herbert Spencer to "Dear Sir," 1872 March 2, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:55)
  Concerning his Principles of Psychology, and explaining "that the medulla [oblongata] is the seat of emotional feeling considered as a mental state apart from the movements it gives rise to."
- Charles Darwin to Virginius Dabney, 1873 November 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:56)
  Concerning the eating habits of caterpillars and hogs. #3082-a.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1874 March 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:57)
  Declining to join a club, written on the front of a lithograph of a general reply to such requests.
- Cha[rles] Lyell to "My dear Sir," 1874 March 19, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:58)
  Concerning his new book, and fossils at Teliscstow.
- Charles Darwin to "My dear Sir," [1875] April 31, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:59)
  Concerning the modification of a species; Darwin's new work on insectivorous plants. Partial envelope pasted to letter; letter brittle; missing portion of letter.
- T[homas] H[enry] Huxley to "Dear Mr. White," 1875 October 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:60)
  Re a friend's address in Naples.
- Charles Darwin to Mrs. S[ophia] B[ledsoe] Herrick, 1876 March 6, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:61)
  Explaining his reasons for believing Drosera was a carnivorous plant. #3361-a.
- Jos[eph] D[alton] Hooker to "My dear Dr. Hoff," 1878 September 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:62)
  Apologizing for the fact that he does not possess another portrait of himself in the Rocky Mountains to give Dr. Hoff.
- Charles Darwin to Virginius Dabney, 1878 October 20, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 1:63)
  Thanking Dabney for his letter, and his trouble in sending a hybrid tomato plant.#3082-a.
- Ch[arles]Darwin to "Dear Sir," 1879 September 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:64)
  Regarding Erasmus Darwin's biography and German and French editions.
- Herbert Spencer to [John] Chapman, 1881 January 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:65)
  Regarding a "mis-statement" by Chapman's wife about Spencer.
- Alfred R[ussel] Wallace to J.E. Jones, 1882 September 10, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:66)
  Regarding omitting "Mr. Sellar's" name from further editions of Wallace's book.
- Herbert Spencer to [Joseph Edgar] Boehm, 1884 February 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:67)
  Regarding obtaining a marble copy of Boehm's bust of Spencer and terra cotta reproductions.
- Herbert Spencer to [Joseph Edgar] Boehm, 1884 July 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:68)
  Regarding two terra cotta busts of Spencer to be sent to George Holme and E.L. Youmans. Hinged to sheet.
- Francis Galton to [William Henry?] Flower, 1884 September 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:69)
  Galton seeks support for his "Anthropometric" apparatus and laboratory.
- Herbert Spencer to [Joseph Edgar] Boehm, 1884 November 7, ALS, 3 pp. to 1 l. (Box-folder 1:70)
  Desiring a plaster cast of himself for Tyndall; suggests changes in the hair on the bust.
- F[rancis]Darwin to W. Beaumont, 1885 September 6, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:71)
  Regarding [James?] Fordyce's Aspects of Religion. Hinged to sheet.
- Herbert Spencer to Editor, Revue des Deux Mondes, 1886 January 19, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:72)
  Concerning publishing two articles he has written titled "The Factors of Organic Evolution." One in which he will criticize Charles Darwin's failure to include "the belief that the inheritance of organic modifications produced by use and disuse, has been a cause of evolution," and that this should be seen as a cooperative cause of evolution.
- Jos[eph] D[alton]Hooker to Dr. Cunningham, 1886 April 14, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:73)
  Introduces a "scientific horticulturalist" who will accompany him on mission to eastern Tibet.
- S[amuel] Butler to Hyde Clark, 1887 December 2, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:74)
  Regarding his theory of unconscious memory; his "personal quarrel" with Charles Darwin, and claims that he has "kept well within the facts-which doubtless is the reason why no answer has ever appeared either from Mr. Charles Darwin or any of his sons." Hinged to sheet.
- Herbert Spencer to Mrs. [John] Chapman, 1895 July 16, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:75)
  Declining to write obituary for Thomas Henry Huxley; requests permission to reprint Dr. Chapman's article, "The Commerce of Literature."
- Francis Galton to "Dear Lady Flower," 1903 July 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:76)
  Regarding scientific differences with William Flower concerning statistical methods.
- Violet Wallace to Pickard Cambridge, 1913 December 5, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:77)
  Requesting any letters or personal reminiscences of her father, Alfred Russel Wallace.
- Thiselton Dyer to "Dear Lankester," 1921 October 5, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:78)
  Concerning [Hugh?] Scott's criticism of Darwinism.
- Cha[rles]Lyell to "Dear Austin," n.y. June 17, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:79)
  Regarding Austin's lectures. Glued to backing.
- Ch[arles] Darwin to unidentified recipient, n.y. November 2, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:80)
  Regarding a theory of language. Darwin responds to this unidentified author's courteous criticism of natural selection. Darwin concludes his letter, "considering what Geology teaches us, the argument for the supposed immutability of specific Types seems to me much the same as if, in a nation which had no old writings, some wise old savage was to say that his language had never changed; but my metaphor is too long to fill up."
- Ch[arles]Darwin to [James Phillip Mansel Weale], n.y. December 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:81)
  Regarding seeds in locust dung germinating; Weale's paper on Bonatea, and mentions that Lyell was going to cite Weale's findings in a new edition of the Principles.
- Ch[arles]Darwin to unidentified recipient, n.y. December 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:82)
  Regarding purchasing books.
- John Playfair to "Dear Madam," n.d. Sunday evening, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:83)
  Regarding lodgings.
- "Note on the Vine," by Dr. Darwin, n.d., AMs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:84)
  Regarding grapes, liquor and results of drinking. Darwin also suggests that this "poison...has thus become the curse of the Christian World." Written on the verso of a flyer for "Willmore's Strawberry and Floral Gardens."
- James Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, n.d., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:85)
  Regarding a recommendation by Marcet.
- J[ames] Hall to Dr. [Alexander John Gaspard] Marcet, n.d., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; postmarked. (Box-folder 1:86)
  Requesting that Marcet not write to Mr. Pictet about a paper.
- List of scientists, including Huxley with brief notes on each, n.d., ANs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:87)
- Envelope with Description of Spencer-Chapman correspondence, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:88)
- Newspaper Clippings, Cartoons and Illustrations Re Charles Darwin, 1863 to 1909, 10 items. (Box-folder 1:89)
- Cartoons and Illustrations Re Charles Darwin, 1863-1909, 15 items; Photocopies. Originals in Oversize Box W-6. (Box-folder 1:90)